<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>java on Jorge Branco&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://jorgedfbranco.github.io/tags/java/</link>
    <description>Recent content in java on Jorge Branco&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jorgedfbranco.github.io/tags/java/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Implementing a Scheduler in Java</title>
      <link>https://jorgedfbranco.github.io/posts/implementing-a-scheduler-in-java/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jorgedfbranco.github.io/posts/implementing-a-scheduler-in-java/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The goal of this article is to implement a simple Scheduler class, allowing us to both schedule tasks (Runnable instances) that are only to be run once, as well as tasks that can be run repeatedly at a given frequency:
interface Scheduler { public void schedule(LocalDateTime startTime, Runnable runnable); public void schedulePeriodic(LocalDateTime startTime, Duration frequency, Runnable runnable); } There are two possible strategies to design such a scheduler:
  Using condition variables - We store submitted tasks in a tasks priority queue, where tasks are ordered by their schedule date.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing a Blocking Queue with Condition Variables</title>
      <link>https://jorgedfbranco.github.io/posts/implementing-a-blocking-queue-with-condition-variables-in-java/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jorgedfbranco.github.io/posts/implementing-a-blocking-queue-with-condition-variables-in-java/</guid>
      <description>A concurrent blocking queue is a special kind of FIFO data-structure where:
 Calling dequeue() always returns an element, blocking the calling thread if the queue is currently empty. Only an insertion by another thread through a call to enqueue(v) will then unblock it; Calling enqueue() inserts an element in the queue. There are two variants of blocking queues: bounded and unbounded. An unbounded queue allows you to insert as many elements on it as you&amp;rsquo;d like.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing an Expression Evaluator with Recursive-Descent Parsing</title>
      <link>https://jorgedfbranco.github.io/posts/writing-an-expression-evaluator-with-recursive-descent-parsing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jorgedfbranco.github.io/posts/writing-an-expression-evaluator-with-recursive-descent-parsing/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Let&amp;rsquo;s consider the problem of implementing a function evalExpr(str): double that, given an arbitrary well-formed mathematical expression, calculates its value.
Examples of such calls and their respective return values would be:
 evalExpr(&amp;quot;1 + 2 * 3 / 4 - 1&amp;quot;) = 1.5. evalExpr(&amp;quot;1 * (2 + 3)&amp;quot;) = 5.  How to go about it? A classical approach to mathematical expression parsing is to use Dijkstra&amp;rsquo;s Shunting-yard algorithm, but in this article we&amp;rsquo;re going to focus on solving it with a recursive-descent parser, as it&amp;rsquo;s a more general approach that also lends itself easier to later expand into a more fully developed language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Introduction to Binary Search</title>
      <link>https://jorgedfbranco.github.io/posts/an-introduction-to-binary-search/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jorgedfbranco.github.io/posts/an-introduction-to-binary-search/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Binary search allows us to quickly &amp;ndash; in &lt;code&gt;O(lg n)&lt;/code&gt; time &amp;ndash; find the index of a value &lt;code&gt;v&lt;/code&gt; in a sorted array &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt;. In other words, binary search is valuable because it spares us from having to exhaustively look for a value in the array (which would have been an &lt;code&gt;O(n)&lt;/code&gt; operation), as long as we know the array to be sorted.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
